I. M. Pei Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
I. M. Pei Papers 1920-2016 1960-2000
MSS83787
Pei, I. M., 1917-2019
180,000 items
534 containers plus 49 oversize
314 linear feet
1,100 digital files (53 GB)
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Architect. Correspondence, planning files, biographical material, maps, blueprints, drawings, proposals, minutes, reports, scrapbooks, press releases, clippings, invitations, brochures, interviews, appointment calendars, travel records, certificates, awards, and photographs related to architectural activities, urban planning, and professional associations of I. M. Pei.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Black, Leicia, approximately 1921-2012.; Breuer, Marcel, 1902-1981--Correspondence.; Chin, Perry Y.; Dreyfuss, Henry, 1904- --Correspondence.; Dubuffet, Jean, 1901-1985--Correspondence.; Ford, O'Neil, 1905-1982--Correspondence.; Franzen, Ulrich, 1921-2012--Correspondence.; Girard, Alexander--Correspondence.; Gropius, Walter, 1883-1969--Correspondence.; Gruen, Victor, 1903-1980--Correspondence.; Hosken, Fran P., 1919-2006--Correspondence.; Ingersoll, R. Sturgis (Robert Sturgis), Sr., 1891-1973--Correspondence.; Johnson, Philip, 1906-2005--Correspondence.; Le Corbusier, 1887-1965--Correspondence.; Matisse, Pierre, 1900-1989--Correspondence.; Mehta, Zubin--Correspondence.; Moore, Henry, 1898-1986--Correspondence.; Nagel, Chester E., 1911- --Correspondence.; Nesjar, Carl, 1920-2015--Correspondence.; Neutra, Richard Joseph, 1892-1970--Correspondence.; Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy, 1929-1994--Correspondence.; Pei family--Correspondence.; Pei, C. C. (Chien Chung); Pei, I. M., 1917-2019.; Pei, Li Chung.; Perlman, Itzhak, 1945- --Correspondence.; Reagan, Ronald--Correspondence.; Robinson, Nancy (Executive assistant); Warnecke, John Carl--Correspondence.; Wen, Jiabao, 1942- --Correspondence.; Yang, Yingfeng, 1926-1997--Correspondence.; Zao, Wou-ki, 1920-2013--Correspondence.; Zeckendorf, William, 1905-1976.
Organizations
Académie d'architecture (France); Académie des beaux-arts (France); American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters.; American Academy of Arts and Sciences.; American Institute of Architects.; American Society of the French Legion of Honor.; Architectural League of New York.; Committee of 100 (New York, N.Y.); Dallas City Hall (Dallas, Tex.); East Building of the National Gallery of Art (Washington, D.C.); Expo (International Exhibitions Bureau) (1970: Osaka, Japan)--Buildings.; Four Seasons Hotel (New York, N.Y.); Harvard University.; I.M. Pei & Associates.; I.M. Pei & Partners.; I.M. Pei Collection (Library of Congress); John F. Kennedy Library.; Massachusetts Institute of Technology Corporation.; Massachusetts Institute of Technology.; Miho Museum.; Morton H. Meyerson Symphony Center.; Museum of Islamic Art (Dawḥah, Qatar); Musée d'art moderne Grand-Duc Jean.; Musée du Louvre.; National Council on the Arts.; National Council on the Humanities.; National Endowment for the Arts.; National Endowment for the Humanities.; Oare Pavilion.; Pei Cobb Freed & Partners.; Pei Partnership Architects.; Raffles City (Singapore); United States. Department of State.; United States. Federal Housing Administration.; Urban Design Council of the City of New York.; Webb & Knapp.
Subjects
AIA Gold Medal.; Architects--Societies, etc.; Architectural design.; Architecture--Awards.; Architecture--Societies, etc.; Architecture.; Art museums--France--Paris.; Art museums--Japan--Shigaraki-chō.; Art museums--Luxembourg--Luxembourg.; Art museums--Qatar--Dawḥah.; Chinese Americans--Societies, etc.; Chinese--Societies, etc.; City planning.; Commercial buildings--New York (State)--New York.; Commercial buildings--Singapore.; Dwellings--England--Wiltshire.; Medal of Liberty.; Music-halls--Texas--Dallas.; Presidential libraries--Massachusetts--Boston.; Pritzker Architecture Prize.; Urban landscape architecture--New York (State)--New York.
Places
Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Boston (Mass.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Dallas (Tex.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Dawḥah (Qatar)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Luxembourg (Luxembourg)--Buildings, structures, etc.; New York (N.Y.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Osaka (Japan)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Paris (France)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Shigaraki-chō (Japan)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Singapore--Buildings, structures, etc.; Wiltshire (England)--Buildings, structures, etc.
Occupations
Architects.
Acquisition Information
The papers of I. M. Pei, architect, were given to the Library of Congress by Pei in 1995. The Library received the collection in numerous accessions between 1996 and 2016.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Some photographic prints, slides, negatives, albums, drawings, and models have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. Some maps have been transferred to the Geography and Maps Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the I. M. Pei Papers.
Access and Restrictions
Restrictions apply governing the use, photoduplication, or publication of items in this collection. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for information concerning these restrictions. In addition, many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Digital Format
Digital files were received as part of the I. M. Pei Papers. Reference copies were created from the original digital media. Advanced notice is required for access to digital content; consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for more information.
Biographical Note
I. M. Pei
Date Event
1917, Apr. 26 Born Ieoh Ming Pei, Canton (Guangzhou), China
1935 Traveled to the United States to study architecture
1940 B.S. in architecture, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Mass.
1942 Married Eileen Loo (died 2014)
1943 1945 Operation analyst, National Defense Research Committee
1945 1948 Assistant professor, Harvard University Graduate School of Design, Cambridge, Mass.
1946 M.S. in architecture, Harvard University Graduate School of Design, Cambridge, Mass.
1948 1955 Director of architecture, Webb & Knapp, Inc.
1954 Became naturalized citizen of the United States
1955 1990 Founded I. M. Pei & Associates (later I. M. Pei & Partners in 1966, and Pei Cobb Freed & Partners in 1989)
1964 Elected fellow, American Institute of Architects
1966 1970 Served on the National Council on the Humanities, appointed by Lyndon B. Johnson
1967 Elected member, American Academy of Arts and Sciences
1975 Elected member, American Academy of Arts and Letters
1975 Elected member, Royal Institute of British Architects
1979 Awarded Gold Medal, American Institute of Architects
1980 Appointed member, National Council on the Arts by Jimmy Carter
1981 Elected member, American Philosophical Society
1981 1984 Member, National Council on the Arts
1983 Awarded Pritzker Architecture Prize
1986 Awarded Medal of Liberty by Ronald Reagan
1988 Awarded National Medal of Art
1990 Retired from Pei Freed Cobb & Partners
1993 Awarded Medal of Freedom by George H. W. Bush
2000 Received Living Legend Award from the Library of Congress
2003 Awarded National Design Award for Lifetime Achievement, Smithsonian Institution, Cooper-Hewitt, National Design Museum
2019, May 16 Died, New York, N.Y.
Chronology of the Work of I. M. Pei
Date Event
1952 1956 Mile High Center, Denver, Colo.
1954 1963 Luce Memorial Chapel, T’ai-chung shih, Taiwain
1957 1962 Kips Bay Plaza, New York, N.Y.
1957 1964 Society Hill, Philadelphia, Pa.
1959 1964 Cecil and Ida Green Center for Earth Sciences, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Mass.
1960 1961 Government Center Urban Renewal Plan, Boston, Mass.
1960 1964 Southwest Washington urban renewal plan, Washington, D.C.
1960 1970 National Airlines Terminal, John F. Kennedy International Airport, New York, N.Y.
1961 1964 Everson Museum of Art, Syracuse, N.Y.
1961 1964 Syracuse University S. I. Newhouse Communications Center, Syracuse, N.Y.
1961 1966 University Plaza, New York University, New York, N.Y.
1961 1967 National Center for Atmospheric Research, Boulder, Colo.
1962 1970 Air traffic control towers, various U.S. airports
1963 1967 New College of Florida dormitories, student union, and academic center, Sarasota, Fla.
1963 1971 Wilmington Tower, Wilmington, Del.
1965 1979 John F. Kennedy Library, Boston, Mass.
1966 1968 Des Moines Art Center addition, Des Moines, Iowa
1966 1969 Bedford-Stuyvesant Superblock, Brooklyn, N.Y.
1966 1971 Cleo Rogers Memorial Library, Columbus, Ind.
1966 1977 Dallas City Hall, Dallas, Tex.
1967 1973 Commerce Court, Canadian Imperial Bank of Commerce, Toronto, Canada
1968 1970 Columbia University Comprehensive Master Plan, New York, N.Y.
1968 1972 Paul Mellon Center for the Arts, Choate Rosemary Hall, Wallingford, Conn.
1968 1973 Herbert F. Johnson Museum of Art, Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y.
1968 1978 East Building of the National Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C.
1970 1976 Oversea-Chinese Banking Corp. Centre, Singapore
1972 1976 Ralph Landau Chemical Engineering Building, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Mass.
1973 1986 Raffles City, Singapore
1974 1983 Johnson & Johnson World Headquarters, New Brunswick, N.J.
1977 1981 Museum of Fine Arts West Wing, Boston, Mass.
1977 1982 Sunning Plaza, Hong Kong
1977 1984 International Business Machines Corp. Corporate Office Building, Purchase, N.Y.
1978 1982 Texas Commerce Tower and United Energy Plaza, Houston, Tex.
1978 1984 Wiesner Building/Center for Arts and Media Technology, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Mass.
1979 1982 Fragrant Hill Hotel, Beijing, China
1979 1986 Jacob K. Javits Convention Center and Plaza, New York, N.Y.
1980 1987 Bank of America Tower at International Plaza, Miami, Fla.
1981 1990 Gateway Towers, Singapore
1981 1992 Guggenheim Pavilion, Mount Sinai Medical Center expansion and modernization, New York, N.Y.
1982 1989 Morton H. Meyerson Symphony Center, Dallas, Tex.
1982 1989 Bank of China Tower, Hong Kong
1983 1989 International Business Machines Corp. Office Building Complex, Somers, N.Y.
1983 1993 Musée du Louvre (Grand Louvre), Paris, France
1986 1989 Choate Rosemary Hall Science Center, Wallingford, Conn.
1987 1995 Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum, Cleveland, Ohio
1988 1990 Shinji Shumeikai Bell Tower, Shiga-ken, Japan
1989 1993 Four Seasons Hotel, New York, N.Y.
1988 1992 Kirklin Clinic, Birmingham, Ala.
1990 2007 Musée d'Art Moderne Grand-Duc Jean, Luxembourg, Luxembourg
1991 1997 Miho Museum, Shiga-ken, Japan
1993 1999 Buck Institute for Age Research, Marin County, Calif.
1994 2001 Bank of China Head Office, Beijing, China
1995 2000 Republic of Korea Permanent Mission to the United Nations, New York, N.Y.
1995 2003 Deutsches Historisches Museum, Berlin, Germany
1996 2001 Ronald Reagan UCLA Medical Center, Los Angeles, Calif.
1999 2003 Oare Pavilion, Wiltshire, England
2000 2008 Museum of Islamic Art, Dawḥah, Qatar
2002 2005 Macau Science Center, Macau, China
2006 2009 Miho Institute of Aesthetics chapel, Shiga-ken, Japan
Scope and Content Note
The papers of I. M. Pei span the years 1920 to 2016, with the bulk of the material dating from 1960 to 2000. The collection documents the professional activities of Pei, best known for his architectural design, which is represented in buildings across the world. Also present in the collection are files related to Pei’s professional associations and activities as an urban planner. Its ten series include General Correspondence, Projects Completed/Inactive, Projects Aborted, Projects Proposed, Publicity File, Scrapbooks, Miscellany, Subject File, Digital Files, and Oversize.
The General Correspondence series documents the broad scope of Pei’s professional associations, activities, and friendships. The correspondence is arranged chronologically by year or year span and alphabetically therein by name of correspondent. The series begins with correspondence dating from Pei’s early career, including his association with William Zeckendorf’s real estate development firm Webb & Knapp, first as architectural director for Zeckendorf, 1948-1955, and then as head of his own firm I. M. Pei & Associates beginning in 1955. The bulk of the series, however, dates after 1960 when Pei’s practice became fully independent of Webb & Knapp. This later material includes some internal memoranda from Pei’s architectural firm, but most of it concerns his professional associations outside his architectural practice. These activities relate to professional organizations including the American Institute of Architects and Architectural League of New York; universities, most notably his alma maters Massachusetts Institute of Technology and Harvard University; galleries and museums; architectural magazines and publishers; the United States government including the Federal Housing Administration and Department of State; and honorary societies and organizations, among them the Académie d’architecture, American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters, American Academy of Arts and Sciences, and American Society of the French Legion of Honor. Correspondents include architects, designers, artists, editors, gallery owners, museum directors, corporate executives, public officials, and university presidents, among others. Prominent correspondents include Marcel Breuer, Henry Dreyfuss, Jean Dubuffet, O’Neil Ford, Ulrich Franzen, Alexander Girard, Walter Gropius, Victor Gruen, Fran P. Hosken, R. Sturgis Ingersoll, Philip Johnson, Pierre Matisse, Henry Moore, Chester E. Nagel, Carl Nesjar, Richard Joseph Neutra, John Carl Warnecke, Yang Yingfeng, and Zao Wou-ki. Letters from other well-known correspondents can be found in the Scrapbooks series. A significant portion of the General Correspondence series documents Pei’s connections with his native China, Taiwan, Hong Kong, Singapore, and the wider Chinese diaspora. Included are letters from family members, friends, architects, artists, students, and various Chinese and Chinese-American organizations. Much of this correspondence is in Mandarin or Cantonese.
The Projects Completed/Inactive series documents projects where Pei was the design principal. Files include projects undertaken by Pei Freed Cobb & Associates and by Pei after his retirement from the firm, yet often in collaboration with Pei Partnership Architects, a firm established in 1992 by Pei’s sons C. C. (Chien Chung) Pei and Li Chung Pei. Most of the projects include corporate headquarters, commercial structures, residential properties, schools, museums, concert halls, transportation terminals, and civic buildings designed by Pei, and in some cases, site plans for urban planning and community development projects. The series has been maintained as it was arranged by Pei’s staff by city, and therein by name of building or project. Most of Pei’s major works are well-documented in the files, most notably the John F. Kennedy Library, Bedford-Stuyvesant Superblock, Raffles City, Morton H. Meyerson Symphony Center, Musée du Louvre, Musée d'Art Moderne Grand-Duc Jean in Luxembourg, and the Miho Museum. The files track project history from the proposal stage to project completion, and sometimes track the subsequent development of the building once the contract has been fulfilled. Typical documents include administrative files including meeting minutes, proposals, contracts, financial documents, memoranda, clippings, studies, reports, blueprints, architectural renderings, plans, drawings, maps, and photographs with a focus on Pei’s personal correspondence with clients, project stakeholders, and contractors. Files maintained after projects have been completed document renovations, historic landmark status, research queries, legal issues, and the evolution of buildings over time. In most cases these are the personal files of Pei, maintained by his executive assistant Leicia Black, and later by her successor, Nancy Robinson. The records of a few projects are much more voluminous and include the files of project manager Perry Y. Chin along with extensive shop drawings and design schematics. These projects include the Museum of Islamic Art, Four Seasons Hotel, and Oare Pavilion. Little documentation exists of early projects from the 1950s when Pei was working exclusively with Webb & Knapp. Also absent from the series are many of Pei’s files relating to the East Building of the National Gallery of Art, which he transferred to the gallery in 1986. There is also no documentation in this series of the air traffic control towers Pei designed for various U.S. airports throughout the 1960s.
The Projects Aborted series contains similar materials as the Projects Completed/Inactive series and likewise tracks the history of various projects. The major difference is that in almost all cases, while the projects were initiated, the buildings were never completed. Pei’s staff chose the designation of “aborted,” but this does not necessarily indicate that Pei intentionally abandoned the project. In most cases, these projects were stalled due to financial, political, or logistical issues. The only exception to this is the China Pavilion at Expo ’70, which was completed, but for which Pei was not the design principal, but rather the supervising architect. The major projects documented in this series include the Bilbao Emblematic Building in Bilbao, Spain; Bank Dagang Nasional Indonesia Center in Jakarta, Indonesia; Château de La Rochefoucauld in France; and the Athens Museum of Contemporary Art in Athens, Greece.
The Projects Proposed series consists of projects declined by Pei, often due to his firm’s heavy workload, or accepted by Pei but later cancelled for a variety reasons. Also included are projects for which Pei’s firm was not selected by the client. The projects represent the type of work for which Pei is best known and largely include institutional and corporate buildings and urban planning projects. Other projects include the 2000 Olympics in Beijing and the design of bottles for L’Oréal perfume and Taittinger champagne. The Projects Proposed series has been maintained as it was arranged by Pei’s staff by year and therein by name of city or country. A list of files (1952-1991) located at the beginning of the series records individual project names. Documentation for the projects, although not extensive in most cases, includes correspondence, memoranda, project proposals and reports, meeting minutes, plans, maps, photographs, financial records, and newspaper clippings. Two sets of report forms on prospective jobs are available for the 1960s and 1970s. These single-sheet summaries record project names, clients, locations, descriptions, and dispositions, and are occasionally supplemented by copies of correspondence and other documentation.
The Publicity File spans Pei’s career and is arranged in three file groupings: general, projects, and speaking engagements. The general file explores the broad scope of Pei’s work as an architect and urban planner from 1946 to 2012. Included are newspaper and magazine articles, book excerpts, and interviews, as well as correspondence with writers, interviewers, and publishers. A bibliography of articles about Pei from 1952 to 1983 follows the general file. The project file documents individual works by Pei and his firm, largely through newspaper and magazine articles. The file is arranged alphabetically by name of city or country and therein by name of project. The speaking engagement file, dated 1979-2012, consists largely of requests for Pei to speak and arrangements for the engagements he accepted. Only a few texts of his remarks are included. The Publicity File overlaps considerably with several other series. Correspondence with writers and publishers, speaking engagement requests, and transcripts of interviews can also be found in the General Correspondence series. The Miscellany series includes acceptance speeches for some of the more major awards received by Pei. The Scrapbooks series overlaps with the Publicity File series to the greatest extent.
Complementing the Publicity File series are more than one hundred volumes of scrapbooks compiled by Pei’s staff. The content of each scrapbook has been rehoused in folders to better preserve the material. Consisting largely of newspaper and magazine articles, the Scrapbooks series includes forty-five general volumes spanning the years 1944 to 2004, as well as separate volumes focusing on specific projects, including Dallas City Hall in Texas, East Building of the National Gallery of Art in Washington, D.C., Grand Louvre in Paris, John F. Kennedy Library in Boston, and Miho Museum in Japan. Four additional volumes contain published interviews with Pei between 1948 and 1989. Six volumes house memorabilia dating from 1960 to 2006. Included are programs and invitations from award ceremonies, building openings, and dinners honoring foreign dignitaries; certificates, awards, and honorary degrees; press releases and some acceptance speeches; a letter from Ronald Reagan congratulating Pei on receipt of the Pritzker Architecture Prize in 1983; and a note dated December 1981 arranging a meeting with François Mitterrand early in the planning process for the renovation and expansion of the Musée du Louvre. Seven scrapbooks contain special letters. Many of the letters are congratulatory notes to Pei on the winning of design competitions, opening of buildings, receipt of awards, and special birthdays. The eclectic range of letters also includes a copy of a 1946 letter from Pei concerning his master’s thesis on a Shanghai art museum, a 1948 letter of appointment from Webb & Knapp, a 1949 letter from Le Corbusier, mentioning Pei’s “maison cylindrique,” a sketch by Pei of the Morton H. Meyerson Symphony Center on the back of an October 1983 incoming letter, a February 1981 letter from Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis about the John F. Kennedy Library, a cheerful postcard from Zubin Mehta and Itzhak Perlman on a trip to China in 1994, and a handwritten letter from Chinese Premier Wen Jiabao on the opening of the Suzhou Museum in 2006.